Guide to the M. Thomas Inge Papers, 1978-1982, 1988-1989 RL.00612
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
M. Thomas Inge papers
1978-1982, 1988-1989
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Inge, M. Thomas
RL.00612
4.6 Linear Feet
5 items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The M. Thomas Inge papers (1978-1989) were donated to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library from 1980-1982 and in 1991 by M. Thomas Inge.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1936, March 18 Born, Newport News, Va.
1959 B.A., Randolph-Macon College
1960 M.A., Vanderbilt University
1962-1964 Instructor of English, Vanderbilt University
1964 Ph.D., Vanderbilt University
1964-1969 Assistant Professor/Associate Professor of American Thought and Language, Michigan State University
1967-1968 Fulbright lecturer, University of Salamanca, Spain
1969-1980 Associate Professor/Professor/Department Chair of English, Virginia Commonwealth University
1970-1979 General Editor, American Critical Tradition series (David Lewis) and Founding Editor, Resources for American Literary Studies
1971 Fulbright lecturer, Buenos Aires, Argentina
1973-1976 General Editor, Research Guides in English (St. Martin's)
1974-1980 Founding Editor, American Humor
1977- General Editor, Research Guides in Popular Culture (Greenwood)
1978 Editor, Handbook of American Popular Culture, Volume 1 (Greenwood); President, American Humor Studies Association
1979 Editor, Bartleby the Inscrutable (Archon); Fulbright lecturer, Moscow State University, U. S. S. R.
1980 Editor, Handbook of American Popular Culture, Volume 2 (Greenwood)
1980- Professor/Department Head of English, Clemson University
1981 Editor, Handbook of American Popular Culture, Volume 3 and Concise Histories of American Popular Culture (Greenwood)
1988 Editor, Handbook of American Popular Literature (Greenwood)
1989 Editor, Handbook of American Popular Culture, 2nd ed., revised and enlarged, 3 vols.
Collection Overview
The M. Thomas Inge Papers (1978-1982, 1988-1989) consist of the corrected manuscripts of five works of which Inge was the editor: Handbook of American Popular Culture (HAPC; 3 vols., 1978-1981), Bartleby the Inscrutable (1979), Concise Histories of American Popular Culture (1981), Handbook of American Popular Literature (1988), and the second edition of HAPC (3 vols., 1989). The Inge papers demonstrate not only the development of M. Thomas Inge's scholarly and editorial acumen, but also the growth of the study of American popular literature and culture.
For Bartleby the Inscrutable, M. Thomas Inge was able to recruit contributions from several important scholars and critics of American literature, including Lewis Leary, Lewis Mumford, Egbert S. Oliver, Alfred Kazin, Richard Chase, Leo Marx, and Hershel Parker.
A member of the American Studies Association, the Modern Language Association, and the Popular Culture Association, M. Thomas Inge edited collections of essays on Faulkner's Light in August, frontier humorists, and Ellen Glasgow before becoming the general editor of Greenwood Press's Research Guides in Popular Culture series in 1977. Inge solicited essays from a number of American cultural studies specialists for the original 1978-1981 HAPC, a project that subsequently led not only to two spinoff projects--the 1981 Concise Histories volume and the 1988 Handbook of American Popular Literature--but also to the 1989 second edition of HAPC. Selected essays in the first edition of HAPC were revised (and abridged) for the Concise Histories volume and further revised either for the Handbook of Popular Literature or for the second edition of HAPC. Thus, by looking in particular at these four items in the Book Manuscripts Series and observing the various additions and deletions, it is possible to trace how several critics--among them James J. Best, Richard Etulain, Katherine Fishburn, Donald A. McQuade, Richard N. Masteller, Nancy Pogel, Janice Radway, Anne E. Rowe, Richard Guy Wilson, and Inge himself--evolved in their views of their areas of specialty.
Collections in the Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library related to the M. Thomas Inge papers include the Lewis Gaston Leary papers, the Lewis Mumford papers, and the Egbert S. Oliver papers.
Popular literature -- United States; Popular culture; Inge, M. Thomas; Melville, Herman, 1819-1891
- Book Manuscripts, 1978-1989
  Scope and Contents note
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Subject Files
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 1st ed., 1978[vol. 1], 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Bartleby the Inscrutable, 1978-1979, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 1st ed., 1980[vol. 2], 5 folders (Box 1)
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 1st ed., 1980-1981[vol. 3], 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 1st ed., 1980-1981[vol. 3], 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Concise Histories of American Popular Culture, 1982, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Handbook of American Popular Literature, 1988, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 2nd ed., 1989, 18 folders (Box 3)
    - Handbook of American Popular Culture, 2nd ed., 1989, 4 folders (Box 4)